<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" ?>
<LanguageData>
	//TO BE PROOFREAD
	<ClickToJumpToProblem>Cliciwch i neidio i'r broblem</ClickToJumpToProblem>
	
	<NeedSawmill>Angen melin lifio</NeedSawmill>
	<NeedSawmillDesc>Mae angen rhiw fath o felin lifio i dorri logiau i fewn i estyll pren amlbwrpas.\n\nAdeiladwch MELIN LIFIO LLAW neu MELIN LIFIO TRYDANOL.</NeedSawmillDesc>
	
	<PoorMood>Hwyliau gwael</PoorMood>
	<PoorMoodDesc>Mae'r gwladychwyr mewn hwyliau gwael a gall achosi chwalfa meddyliol bach ar unrhyw bryd:\n\n{0}</PoorMoodDesc>
	
	<TerribleMood>Hwyliau ofnadwy</TerribleMood>
	<TerribleMoodDesc>Mae'r gwladychwyr mewn hwyliau ofnadwy a gall arwain at chwalfa meddyliol caled - a hyd yn oed fod yn dreisgar:\n\n{0}</TerribleMoodDesc>
	
	<LowMoodDescEnding>Gwiriwch tab Anghenion y gwladychwyr hyn i weld beth sy'n eu poeni.</LowMoodDescEnding>
	
	<ColonistNeedsRescue>Gwladychwr angen ei arbed</ColonistNeedsRescue>
	<ColonistsNeedRescue>Gwladychwyr angen eu arbed</ColonistsNeedRescue>
	<ColonistsNeedRescueDesc>Mae'r gwladychwyr hyn yn analleuog ar y llawr:\n\n{0}\nGyrwch gwladychwr arall i'w arbed a'i gario nhw nol i'w gwleyau.\n\n(I'w achub, dewiswch gwladychwr arall, cliciwch y botwm dde a dewiswch Arbed.</ColonistsNeedRescueDesc>
	
	<BuildARoom>Adeiladu ystafell</BuildARoom>
	<BuildARoomDesc>Mae ystafell yn cynnwys darnau wal ar wahân gyda drws.\n\nDewiswch y ddewislen Pensaer ar waelod chwith y sgrin er mwyn ddynodi ble rydych am adeiladu. Unwaith y byddwch yn dynodi rhywbeth i gael ei hadeiladu, bydd eich gwladychwyr yn gwneud y gwaith pan y gallan.</BuildARoomDesc>
	
	<NeedDefenses>Angen amddiffynfeydd</NeedDefenses>
	<NeedDefensesDesc>Rydych chi wedi bod yma peth amser ac wedi cael eich gweld yn ôl pob tebyg. Bydd cyrchoedd môr-ladron yn dechrau cyn bo hir.\n\nDylech baratoi amddiffynfeydd, boed yn drapiau, bagiau tywod, neu tyredau.</NeedDefensesDesc>
	
	<NeedDoctor>Angen meddyg</NeedDoctor>
	<NeedDoctorDesc>Mae'r gwladychwyr hyn angen gofal meddygol, ond nid oes gennych unrhyw wladychwyr iach wedi'w aseinio fel meddyg.\n\n{0}\nAseiniwch wladychwr iach i'r weithra Meddyg. Os na chaiff ei drin, gall clwyfau byth eu wella'n iawn a allai'n y pendraw fod yn barhaol.</NeedDoctorDesc>
	
	<NeedMiner>Angen mwynwr</NeedMiner>
	<NeedMinerDesc>Yr ydych wedi dynodi creigiau i'w cloddio ond does dim gwladychwr wedi'w aseinio i'r weithra Mwynwr.\n\nAseiniwch wladychwr i'r weithra Mwynwr.</NeedMinerDesc>
	
	<NeedWarden>Angen warden</NeedWarden>
	<NeedWardenDesc>Mae gennych garcharor, ond dim wladychwr wedi'w aseinio i'r weithra Warden.\n\nAseiniwch wladychwr i'r weithra Warden.</NeedWardenDesc>
	
	<LowFood>Bwyd isel</LowFood>
	<LowFoodDesc>Oes gennych ond {0} unedau o fwyd ar ôl yn eich storfa. Mae hyn yn beryglus o isel.\n\nTyfwch, prynwch, dod o hyd, neu lladd er mwyn cael bwyd.</LowFoodDesc>
	
	<LowMedicine>Meddygaeth isel</LowMedicine>
	<LowMedicineDesc>Oes gennych ond {0} meddyginiaethau ar ôl yn eich storfa.\n\nPrynwch fwy o feddyginiaeth gan fasnachwyr.</LowMedicineDesc>
	
	<NoMedicineDesc>Does dim meddyginiaeth ar ôl yn eich storfa.\n\nPrynwch fwy o feddyginiaeth gan fasnachwyr.</NoMedicineDesc>
	
	<NeedColonistBeds>Angen gwelyau gwladychwyr</NeedColonistBeds>
	<NeedColonistBedsDesc>Mae mwy o wladychwyr yma na sydd o welyau ar eu gyfer. Bydd dim lle i gysgu i rhiwun.\n\nNaill ai gwnewch mwy o welyau, neu newidiwch wely garcharor i wely gwladychwr. \n\nOs nad oes gennych adnoddau, mae mannau cysgu am ddim a gellir eu gosod ar unwaith.</NeedColonistBedsDesc>
	
	//TODO
	
	<HunterLacksWeapon>Hunter lacks weapon</HunterLacksWeapon>
	<HunterLacksWeaponDesc>A colonist is assigned as a hunter but has no weapon. They will not hunt until they are carrying a weapon.\n\nTo reduce injury, we recommend giving them a ranged weapon.</HunterLacksWeaponDesc>
	
	<Starvation>Starvation</Starvation>
	<StarvationDesc>These colonists are starving:\n\n{0}\nGet them some food.</StarvationDesc>
	
	<StarvationAnimals>Animal starvation</StarvationAnimals>
	<StarvationAnimalsDesc>These colony animals are starving:\n\n{0}\nGet them some food.</StarvationAnimalsDesc>
	
	<Exhaustion>Exhaustion</Exhaustion>
	<ExhaustionDesc>These colonists are exhausted and need rest:\n\n{0}\nGet them some rest. They'll need a bed marked for colonist use. Also, make sure they're not drafted.</ExhaustionDesc>
	
	<NeedFoodHopper>Need food hopper</NeedFoodHopper>
	<NeedFoodHopperDesc>You have a nutrient dispenser with no hopper next to it.\n\nTo work, paste dispensers must draw from an adjacent hopper filled with raw food.\n\nBuild a hopper adjacent to the dispenser.</NeedFoodHopperDesc>
	
	<BuildingNeedsPower>Building needs power</BuildingNeedsPower>
	<BuildingsNeedPower>Buildings need power</BuildingsNeedPower>
	<BuildingsNeedPowerDesc>These power-using buildings are totally disconnected from all possible power sources:\n\n{0}\nConnect them to a power generator or battery.</BuildingsNeedPowerDesc>
	
	<AndMore>and more</AndMore>
	
	<NeedMealSource>Need meal source</NeedMealSource>
	<NeedMealSourceDesc>You have no way of preparing proper meals from raw food.\n\nBuild a stove, campfire, or nutrient dispenser.\n\n(It cannot be in a prison cell, otherwise colonists cannot use it.)</NeedMealSourceDesc>
	
	<NeedHomeArea>Need home area</NeedHomeArea>
	<NeedHomeAreaDesc>You need to define a HOME AREA where your colonists will clean, extinguish fires, and repair things.\n\nDefine a home area using the ZONES section of the ARCHITECT menu.</NeedHomeAreaDesc>
	
	<NeedBatteries>Need batteries</NeedBatteries>
	<NeedBatteriesDesc>You only have solar generators and no batteries. This means you'll lose power every time the sun goes down.\n\nBuild a battery or two to get you through the night.</NeedBatteriesDesc>
	
	<NoTradingCapacity>No trading capacity</NoTradingCapacity>
	<NoTradingCapacityDesc>You have no way of trading with passing ships.\n\nBuild a comms console.</NoTradingCapacityDesc>
	
	<BrawlerHasRangedWeapon>Brawler has ranged weapon</BrawlerHasRangedWeapon>
	<BrawlerHasRangedWeaponDesc>One of your colonists has the Brawler personality trait, but is carrying a ranged weapon. This will make them very unhappy.</BrawlerHasRangedWeaponDesc>
	
	<ShieldUserHasRangedWeapon>Shield user has ranged weapon</ShieldUserHasRangedWeapon>
	<ShieldUserHasRangedWeaponDesc>One of your colonists has a personal shield and is carrying a ranged weapon. They will not be able to fire their weapon through the shield (except at targets who are already touching them).</ShieldUserHasRangedWeaponDesc>
	
	<NeedResearchProject>Need research project</NeedResearchProject>
	<NeedResearchProjectDesc>You have the equipment to do research but have not selected a project.\n\nOpen the research menu and select a project.</NeedResearchProjectDesc>
	
	<NeedDump>Need dump</NeedDump>
	<NeedDumpDesc>You have marked {0} to be hauled, but the colonists have nowhere to take it.\n\nDesignate a stockpile and set its storage settings to accept {0}.</NeedDumpDesc>
	<!-- Removed <NeedGrave>Need grave</NeedGrave> <NeedGraveDesc>There is a dead body laying on the ground and nowhere for your colonists to take it.\n\nBuild a grave or a dumping zone and set their storage settings.</NeedGraveDesc> -->
	
	<ColonistsIdle>{0} colonists idle</ColonistsIdle>
	<ColonistsIdleDesc>These colonists are wandering idly:\n\n{0}\nYou should probably find them something productive to do.</ColonistsIdleDesc>
	<!-- Removed <HaltedConstructions>{0} constructions are missing materials</HaltedConstructions> <HaltedConstructionsDesc>These kinds of constructions are missing materials:\n\n{0}\nYou should probably make required materials available for your colonists.</HaltedConstructionsDesc> -->
	
	<ColonistNeedsTreatment>Colonist needs treatment</ColonistNeedsTreatment>
	<ColonistNeedsTreatmentDesc>These colonists need medical treatment. Without it, they may die of their wounds, or their wounds may become permanent.\n\n{0}\nTreat them by sending them to a medical bed.\n\n(First, assign a medical bed by selecting it and toggling it into a medical bed. Then, select the wounded colonists and right-click on the medical bed to make them a patient.)</ColonistNeedsTreatmentDesc>
	
	<AlertHypothermia>Hypothermia</AlertHypothermia>
	<AlertHypothermiaDesc>These colonists are suffering from hypothermia.\n\n{0}\nMake sure their clothing is appropriate for the season and that indoor spaces are properly heated.</AlertHypothermiaDesc>
	
	<PatientsAwaitingMedicalOperation>{0} patients await medical operation</PatientsAwaitingMedicalOperation>
	<PatientsAwaitingMedicalOperationDesc>These patients await medical operation:\n\n{0}\nMake sure you have all necessary medical tools and a free doctor available.</PatientsAwaitingMedicalOperationDesc>
	
	<FireInHomeArea>Fire!</FireInHomeArea>
	<FireInHomeAreaDesc>There is a fire in the home area.</FireInHomeAreaDesc>
	
	<PawnsWithLifeThreateningDisease>Severe illness</PawnsWithLifeThreateningDisease>
	<PawnsWithLifeThreateningDiseaseDesc>People are at risk of death because of severe illness:\n\n{0}\nMake sure that they get the best medical possible.</PawnsWithLifeThreateningDiseaseDesc>
	<PawnsWithLifeThreateningDiseaseAmputationDesc>People are at risk for death because of severe illness:\n\n{0}\nIf possible, consider amputating or replacing infected limbs in order to keep colonists alive.</PawnsWithLifeThreateningDiseaseAmputationDesc>
	
	<BilliardsNeedsSpace>Billiards needs space</BilliardsNeedsSpace>
	<BilliardsNeedsSpaceDesc>One of your billiards table is adjacent to an obstruction that will prevent colonists from using it.\n\nA billiards table needs clear space around it on all sides to be usable.</BilliardsNeedsSpaceDesc>
	
	<HunterHasShieldAndRangedWeapon>Hunter has shield and ranged weapon</HunterHasShieldAndRangedWeapon>
	<HunterHasShieldAndRangedWeaponDesc>One of your hunters is using a ranged weapon and wearing a personal shield which prevents shooting at range.\n\nThey won't be able to hunt unless the shield is removed.</HunterHasShieldAndRangedWeaponDesc>

	<NeedWarmClothes>Need warm clothes</NeedWarmClothes>
	<NeedWarmClothesDesc1>At least {0} of your colonists will lack warm clothes when the cold season comes.</NeedWarmClothesDesc1>
	<NeedWarmClothesDesc1All>All of your colonists will lack warm clothes when the cold season comes.</NeedWarmClothesDesc1All>
	<NeedWarmClothesDesc2>The outdoor temperature is going to reach {0}.\n\nYou can tailor warm clothes at the tailoring bench, or buy them from traders.</NeedWarmClothesDesc2>

	<ImmobileCaravan>Immobile caravan</ImmobileCaravan>
	<ImmobileCaravanDesc>One of your caravans is immobile because it carries too much.\n\nYou can make the caravan mobile again by abandoning some items in the ITEMS tab.</ImmobileCaravanDesc>
	
</LanguageData>
